NROTC/V-12 Collection MS029
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
NROTC/V-12 Collection
1941 -- 1945
1938 -- 2011
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
NROTC/V-12
MS029
37.5 Linear Feet 26 oversize boxes, 5 letter size document boxes, 3 flag boxes, 2 record cartons, 2 half letter size document boxes, 1 legal size document box, and 1 oversize folder
10 Volumes
34 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series: Memorabilia; Publications; Exhibit Materials; Photographs.
Custodial History
Donated from various Tufts NROTC/V-12 veterans.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains Navy V-12 Program publications, scrapbook, sword, aviation equipment, and military accessories. Also included are records from Army ROTC.
Related Materials
Objects related to the NROTC may be found in the David and Howard Arthur Lincon Collection (MS035).
Biographical / Historical
The Navy V-12 Program was established in 1942 as part of the Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps to provide accelerated officer training at American colleges and universities in support of the war effort. During its existence at Tufts, more than 4,000 officers received their training on the Medford campus. Students enrolled in the program were able to complete their college studies, supplemented with special military training, prior to being commissioned in the navy. The School for War Service was organized to administer the naval programs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
V-12 Program, United States. Dept. of the Navy; United States. Navy. Reserve Officers' Training Corps; World War, 1939-1945; University history
- Memorabilia, 1941 -- 2008; 1941 -- 1945; MS029.001; 12.0 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains memorabilia donated by various Tufts V-12/NROTC veterans, including a dress sword, class ring, aviation equipment, and midshipman's and officer's hats.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as found.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - U.S. NROTC Tufts cadet visor midshipman's hat, 1942; MS029.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Black visor.
    Cap, Service; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), white beret, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    Donor: Michele Gerety. Andrew F. Lentine's uniform (instructor at Tufts). These dates are approximate. Associated material can be found at MS029/001-017#00005-00010 and MS029/001-002#00002-00005.
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), black beret, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), gray wedge cap, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), gray beret, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Navy officer's summer visor hat, 1944; MS029.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    Donor: Peter Merenda
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), white beret, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
    Donor: Michele Gerety. Andrew F. Lentine's uniform (instructor at Tufts). These dates are approximate. Associated material can be found at MS029/001-017#00005-00010 and MS029/001-001#00002-00005.
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), tan beret, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), black beret, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), white beret, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook, pp 1-42, 1941 -- 1945; MS029.001.003.001 (Box Shared 74)
    Scrapbook divided into 3 boxes. This box contains pages 1-42. The scrapbook was created and maintained by the V-12/NROTC staff and was housed in their offices. Bill Kirkpatrick E'46 had a son who was in the last NROTC class at Tufts and he saved the book from being thrown away. The scrapbook was given by Kirkpatrick (the son) to Bill Kirkpatrick for his 50th reunion, after which it was given to Herbert Nelson E'46 for safekeeping because Nelson lived on Cape Cod and Kirkpatrick lived in California and did not want to take it back across country with him. John Rodgers learned of its whereabouts and transported it to Tufts University Archives in 2000.
    Scrapbook; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps
  - Scrapbook, pp 43-84, 1941 -- 1945; MS029.001.004.001 (Box 4)
    Scrapbook divided into 3 boxes. This box contains pages 43-84. The scrapbook was created and maintained by the V-12/NROTC staff and was housed in their offices. Bill Kirkpatrick E'46 had a son who was in the last NROTC class at Tufts and he saved the book from being thrown away. The scrapbook was given by Kirkpatrick (the son) to Bill Kirkpatrick for his 50th reunion, after which it was given to Herbert Nelson E'46 for safekeeping because Nelson lived on Cape Cod and Kirkpatrick lived in California and did not want to take it back across country with him. John Rodgers learned of its whereabouts and transported it to Tufts University Archives in 2000.
  - Scrapbook, pp 85-128, 1941 -- 1945; MS029.001.005.001 (Box 5)
    Scrapbook divided into 3 boxes. This box contains pages 85-128. The scrapbook was created and maintained by the V-12/NROTC staff and was housed in their offices. Bill Kirkpatrick E'46 had a son who was in the last NROTC class at Tufts and he saved the book from being thrown away. The scrapbook was given by Kirkpatrick (the son) to Bill Kirkpatrick for his 50th reunion, after which it was given to Herbert Nelson E'46 for safekeeping because Nelson lived on Cape Cod and Kirkpatrick lived in California and did not want to take it back across country with him. John Rodgers learned of its whereabouts and transported it to Tufts University Archives in 2000.
  - Naval aviator's kneeboard, 1967 -- 1969; MS029.001.006.00001 (Box 6)
    Donor: John A. Hickey. Kneeboard is worn strapped to aviator's knee, giving him a writing surface when needed. Also holds or displays documents required for mission. Attached to knee board are the Air Traffic Control guidelines for flight operations flying for the U.S.S. Intrepid.
    Board; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Naval aviator's air navigation computer, 1967 -- 1969; MS029.001.006.00002 (Box 6)
    Donor: John A. Hickey. Computer used for computing the aircraft's flight path, incoprorating such items as wind speed and direction, and correction of aircraft's airspeed based on altitude and other considerations.
    Computer; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Naval aviator's flight helmet, 1967 -- 1969; MS029.001.007.001 (Box 7)
    Donor: John A. Hickey. Helmet is decorated in the squadron colors for Helicopter Combat Support Squadron Two (HC-2) who were nicknamed "Fleet Angels" for their role in the rescue of downed aviators. As Officer-in-Charge of the rescue detachment, John A. Hickey wore this helmet during the period 1967-1969 on board the aircraft carrier U.S.S. Intrepid (CVA-11) off the coast of Vietnam.
    Helmet; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps
  - Naval aviator's oxygen mask, 1967 -- 1969; MS029.001.008.001 (Box 8)
    Donor: John A. Hickey. This oxygen mask was required for flight above 10,000 feet (but not in helicopters).
    Mask; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps
  - Warren Jackson's scrapbook of NROTC at Tufts, 1943 -- 1946; MS029.001.009.001 (Box 9)
    Donor: Warren Jackson. Scrapbook includes documentation and correspondence regarding Jackson's experience in the NROTC program. Also, dance cards, news clippings, and postcards.
  - Khaki visor cap cover, 1944; MS029.001.010.00001 (Box 10)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Cover has lining. Size 6 & 7/8
  - Black visor cover, 1955; MS029.001.010.00002 (Box 10)
    Donor: Matt Burns. Intials "MJB" stenciled in white on inside of cover. This date is approximate.
  - Black wool visor cover, 1955; MS029.001.010.00003 (Box 10)
    Donor: Matt Burns. This date is approximate.
  - Khaki visor cover, 1955; MS029.001.010.00004 (Box 10)
    Donor: Matt Burns. Cover has no lining. Initials "MIB" and "MJB" written on inside. This date is approximate.
  - White Naval dress gloves, 1955; MS029.001.010.00005 (Box 10)
    Donor: Matt Burns. Note- pair consists of 2 right-handed gloves. This date is approximate.
  - Ensign's epaulettes, 1944; MS029.001.011.00001 (Box 11)
    Epaulettes; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Campaign ribbon: WWII victory medal, WWII navy occupation, Philippine liberation medal, 1945; MS029.001.011.00002 (Box 11)
    Donor: Jason H. Samuels. This date is approximate.
    Ribbon; Pins; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Campaign ribbon: American campaign, Euorpe, African, Middle East campaign, Asiatic Pacific campaign (two stars)., 1945; MS029.001.011.00003 (Box 11)
  - U.S. Naval ROTC Ring, 1941 -- 1945; MS029.001.011.00004 (Box 11)
    Donated by Ellie Short representing Peter Merenda.
  - Emblem Pin, 1941 -- 1945; MS029.001.011.00005 (Box 11)
  - Commemorative Navy plaque, MS029.001.012.001 (Box 12)
    No date. Plaque awarded to Tufts College by the Secretary of the Navy, James Forrestal.
    Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Sword belt of naval officer, 1944; MS029.001.013.001 (Box 13)
  - Sword of naval officer, 1944; MS029.001.014.001 (Box 14)
  - Peter Merenda documents and photographs, 1943 -- 1944; MS029.001.015.00001 (Box 15)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Folder includes several photographs of Merenda in uniform, 3 Naval ID cards, certificate of Naval Training program completion, letter from Capt. Haines, an application for National Service Life Insurance, and appointment in Naval Reserve form.
    Merenda, Peter F.
  - Visit to submarine base notification, 1903 -- 1943; MS029.001.015.00002 (Box 15)
  - Matt Burns correspondence, 1953; MS029.001.015.00003 (Box 15)
    Donor: Matt Burns. Folder includes correspondence between Matt Burns and the NROTC program regarding his application and enrollment in the program.
  - U.S. NROTC Commissioning Exercises program, 1946; MS029.001.015.00004 (Box 15)
    Donor: Rev. Donald R. Grinidey.
  - Freshman class enrollment in NROTC unit, 1941; MS029.001.015.00005 (Box 15)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Naval Science Memorandum No. 1.
  - Enlistment of Naval ROTC students, 1942; MS029.001.015.00006 (Box 15)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Letter from Captain Kepler, USN.
  - Surveys of first NROTC class at Tufts, 1984; MS029.001.015.00007 (Box 15)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Folder 4 includes letter from Peter Merenda to Junie Beers regarding a Criterion article about the NROTC. Also included are answered surveys by former ROTC members regarding their expereince in the program.
  - Tufts publications featuring NROTC, 1954 -- 1985; MS029.001.015.00008 (Box 15)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Tufts Criterion, June 1969. Tufts Weekly, March 25, 1954. Tufts Criterion, Spring 1985. Copies not bound. May be used for display.
  - Speech notes from NROTC Memorial dedication ceremony, 1998; MS029.001.015.00009 (Box 15)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Notes from speech given at memorial dedication ceremony. Memories of time spent in Navy program at Tufts.
  - Three NROTC Photographs, 1945 -- 1946; MS029.001.015.00010 (Box 15)
    Donated by William Robinson Hooper, E'46. One image labeled "Civil Engineering Class of 1946." The second image is labeled "Delts 1945" and the third image is unlabeled.
  - U.S. Navy ribbon, 1941; MS029.001.016.00001 (Box 16)
    Donor: Russell Babcock. Black ribbon with U.S. Navy stenciled on front. This date is approximate.
    Ribbon; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Navy woodblock stamp, MS029.001.016.00002 (Box 16)
    Section 2 in box.
  - Bugle band patch, 1941; MS029.001.016.00003 (Box 16)
    Donor: Russell Babcock. Section 3 in box. This date is approximate.
    Patch; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Purple heart awarded to Richard Roy Phillips, 1944; MS029.001.016.00004 (Box 16)
    Came through Rocco Carzo at Department of Athletics as part of 2005.024.
  - Academic achievement medal, 1944; MS029.001.016.00005 (Box 16)
    Section 6 in box. Highest Scholastic Standing Award presented to Arthur R. Foster, May 1944. NROTC, Tufts College. Section 12 in box. Arrived in box addressed to Art Foster from Joe Dundore.
  - NROTC graduation ring, 1944; MS029.001.016.00006 (Box 16)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Section 8 in box.
    Signet Ring; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Midshipman insignia pin, 1953; MS029.001.016.00007 (Box 16)
    USN ROTC pin. Section 9 in box. This date is approximate.
  - U.S. Navy league pin with anchor, 1941; MS029.001.016.00008 (Box 16)
    Donor: Jason H. Samuels. Section 10 in box. This date is approximate.
    Pins; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Navy league of U.S. pin with eagle, 1941; MS029.001.016.00009 (Box 16)
    Donor: Jason H. Samuels. Section 11 in box. This date is approximate.
  - Identification Bracelet, 1944; MS029.001.016.00010 (Box 16)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. Section 4 in box. This bracelet was a supplement to the ID tags worn by naval ensigns. It is inscribed with information about the donor, including his Navy officer's file number blood type, and religion.
  - Watch, 1941; MS029.001.016.00011 (Box 16)
    Donor: Peter Merenda. This is the watch he was instructed by the U.S. Navy to buy in preparation for deployment on a Mine Sweeper during World War II. Its features, such as a luminous dial and non-magnetic aluminum construction made it particularly suited for this work. The current watch band is not the original band.
    NROTC; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps
  - Naval jacket, summer dress whites, 1952; MS029.001.017.00001 (Box 17)
    Donor: David Lincoln. White naval jacket of heavy cotton material. Epaulettes attached to shoulders and brass buttons. This date is approximate.
  - Wool naval jacket, 1952; MS029.001.017.00002.1 (Box 17)
    Donor: David Lincoln. Belong to MS029/001-017 #002.2 Double breasted wool jacket, navy in color. Two rows of gold ribbon around cuffs and one gold star on each sleeve. This date is approximate.
  - Wool naval pants, 1952; MS029.001.017.00002.2 (Box 17)
    Donor: David Lincoln. Pants are navy in color. Belong to MS029/001-017 #002.1. This date is approximate.
  - Khaki naval jacket, 1952; MS029.001.017.00003.1 (Box 17)
    Donor: David Lincoln. Belongs with MS029/001-017#003.2. Single breasted suit jacket with 3 brass buttons and 4 front pockets. Black epaulettes attached to shoulders. Some small moth holes. This date is approximate.
  - Khaki naval pants, 1952; MS029.001.017.00003.2 (Box 17)
    Donor: David Lincoln. Belongs to MS029/001-017 #003.1. This date is approximate.
  - Naval shirt, undressed whites, 1952; MS029.001.017.00004 (Box 17)
    Donor: David Lincoln. Object currently in exhibit case (as of Spring 2001). Heavy white cotton shirt with D.Lincoln stenciled on front. Some stains and discoloration. This date is approximate.
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), navy jacket with gold buttons, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.017.00005 (Box 17)
    Donor: Michele Gerety. Andrew F. Lentine's uniform (instructor at Tufts). These dates are approximate. Associated material can be found at MS029/001-001#00002-00005 and MS029/001-002#00002-00005.
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), white jacket with gold buttons, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.017.00006 (Box 17)
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), tan jacket with gold buttons, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.017.00007 (Box 17)
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), gray jacket with black buttons, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.017.00008 (Box 17)
  - V-12 military program (instructor's uniform), tan button-down shirt, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.017.00009 (Box 17)
  - Andrew F. Lentine, biographical material, 1943 -- 2008; MS029.001.017.00010 (Box 17)
    Donor: Michele Gerety. These dates are approximate. Associated material can be found at MS029/001-001#00002-00005 and MS029/001-002#00002-00005.
  - NROTC photographs, 1943 -- 1945; MS029.001.017.00011 (Box 17)
    Donor: Michele Gerety and Patricia Callahan. These dates are approximate. Contains two photographs of Chief Sp. Andrew Lentine and one photograph labelled, Company 5- Color Company- Tufts College, June 1945 - Co. Commander- R.F. Carlson.
  - "To the Navy at Tufts College," poem by John Holmes, MS029.001.019.00001 (Box Large Map Case 3 Drawer 8)
    No date.
    NROTC; Holmes, John
  - Navigation science class papers, 1943; MS029.001.035.00001 (Box 35)
  - Photographs of Peter Merenda, 1945; MS029.001.035.00002 (Box 35)
  - Peter Merenda's U. S. Naval Reserve identification card, 1965; MS029.001.035.00003 (Box 35)
  - Peter Merenda's U. S. Naval Reserve identification card, 1955; MS029.001.035.00004 (Box 35)
  - Peter Merenda's U. S. Naval Reserve Drill Reporting Card, MS029.001.035.00005 (Box 35)
  - American Flag, 1999; MS029.001.036 (Box 36)
    Tassle included in box. Two-part flag poles are located by the pink barcode area of the stacks. The flag base is located under the card catalog to the left of the stacks door.
  - Marine Corps Flag, 1999; MS029.001.037 (Box 37)
  - U.S. Navy Flag, 1999; MS029.001.038 (Box 38)
  - My nearly forty-two years of service in the U.S. Navy and Navy Reserve, 2006; MS029.001.039.00001; Merenda, Peter F. (Box 39)
  - 4 Naval Ribbons, 1942 -- 1945; MS029.001.039.00002 (Box 39)
    American Theater - Atlantic WWII; WWII Victory; National Defense WWII; and Active Navy Reserve
  - Shoulder boards, Captain USNR, 1965; MS029.001.039.00003 (Box 39)
    Purchased by Peter Merenda at the Naval Base in Newport when he was selected for Captain in February 1965.
  - Shirt collar devices (Insignia 0-6 Eagles), 1945; MS029.001.039.00004 (Box 39)
    Donated by Peter Merenda.
  - Peter Merenda NROTC schedules, memos, ID card, and correspondence, circa 1941 -- 1944; MS029.000185 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Transferred by Margot D. Lenhart on behalf of Peter F. Merenda, 2019, accession MS-2020-011.
    Peter Merenda's Navy ID; schedules, memo, and instructions for NROTC students at Tufts; note to Merenda from Dean Wessell; and copies of Tufts Weekly from 1941.
  - Navy uniform components, circa 1980; MS029.000188
    Peter Merenda's bow tie, cummerbund, gloves, cufflinks, and other Navy uniform components.
- Publications, 1938 -- 1962; 1941 -- 1945; MS029.002; 1.25 Linear Feet; 10 Volumes
  This series contains publications relating to NROTC/V-12. The "Tufts Tracer" NROTC/V-12 student paper started in September 1941 and published inconsistently until June 1943 when it became more professional and was published bimonthly. Present from years 1941-57. The "Shakedown" is the Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps yearbook. First issue 1946.
  This series is arranged chronologically within each publication.
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1942-09; MS029.002.018.00001 (Box 18)
    Donor: Warren E. Jackson
    Volume, issue
    2, 1
    Tufts Tracer; World War, 1939-1945; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1943-05; MS029.002.018.00002 (Box 18)
    2, 2
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1943-09; MS029.002.018.00003 (Box 18)
    Donor: Warren E. Jackson.
    3, 1
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1943-11; MS029.002.018.00004 (Box 18)
    3, 2
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1944-01; MS029.002.018.00005 (Box 18)
    3, 3
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1944-03; MS029.002.018.00006 (Box 18)
    3, 4
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1944-05; MS029.002.018.00007 (Box 18)
    3, 5
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1944-09; MS029.002.018.00008 (Box 18)
    4, 1
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1944-11; MS029.002.018.00009 (Box 18)
    4, 2
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1945-01; MS029.002.018.00010 (Box 18)
    4, 3
  - The Tufts Tracer, 1945-03; MS029.002.018.00011 (Box 18)
    4, 4
  - The Tufts Tracer Graduation Issue, 1945-09; MS029.002.018.00012 (Box 18)
    5, 1
    Tufts Tracer; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - The Tufts Tracer Graduation Issue NROTC and V-12 Classes, 1946-02; MS029.002.018.00013 (Box 18)
    Donor: Donald R. Grindy
    5, 4
  - Tufts Tracer, 1941-11; MS029.002.018.00014 (Box 18)
    Donor: Peter Merenda.
    1, 1
  - Tufts Tracer, 1941-12; MS029.002.018.00015 (Box 18)
  - Shakedown: Yearbook of the Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps, 1946; MS029.002.020.001 (Box Volume 20)
  - Naval Administration, 1943; MS029.002.021.00001 (Box 21)
    Donor: Warren Jackson. Book used for Naval Administration and Leadership
    course at Tufts.
    Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Naval Research Reviews, Jan., 1962; MS029.002.021.00002 (Box 21)
  - Your Boys and the ROTC, Mar., 1953; MS029.002.021.00003 (Box 21)
    Donor: Matt Burns. Written by Harold W. Dodds. Reprinted from Atlantic
    Monthly, Mar. 1953.
  - The Ships and Aircraft of the U.S. Fleet, 1944; MS029.002.021.00004 (Box 21)
    Donor: Warren Jackson. A supplementary text for the daily program of
    recognition of U.S. Allied and enemy ships and aircraft.
  - Our Navy, Mid-September, 1944; MS029.002.022.00001 (Box 22)
  - Our Navy, May 1, 1945; MS029.002.022.00002 (Box 22)
  - Our Navy, Mid-June, 1945; MS029.002.022.00003 (Box 22)
  - Our Navy, Jan. 1, 1945; MS029.002.022.00004 (Box 22)
  - Our Navy, Mid-Feb., 1945; MS029.002.022.00005 (Box 22)
  - Our Navy, Aug. 1, 1945; MS029.002.022.00006 (Box 22)
  - Our Navy, Mid-Sept., 1945; MS029.002.022.00007 (Box 22)
  - Watch Officer's Guide, 1941; MS029.002.023.001 (Box Volume 23)
    Donor: Warren Jackson. Reference recommended for personal library of all
    Naval line officers. NROTC curriculum.
  - The Bluejackets Manual, 1940; MS029.002.024.001 (Box Volume 24)
    Donor: Warren Jackson. A basic reference for all Naval
    Personnel.
  - The Naval Officer's Guide, 1944; MS029.002.025.001 (Box Volume 25)
    Donor: Warren Jackson. A reference book purchased by all NROTC Midshipmen
    prior to commissioning. It is the reference for "what to expect" when commissioned
    from uniforms, to Division Officer duties, to Social rules of etiquette,
    etc.
  - Naval Machinery, 1941; MS029.002.026.001 (Box Volume 26)
    Donor: Warren Jackson. This is the textbook used in the Naval Engineering
    Course.
  - American Practical Navigator, 1938; MS029.002.027.001 (Box Volume 27)
    Donor: Warren Jackson. This is the bible for Marine Navigation and the
    reference for the basic (piloting) and advanced (celestial) navigation
    courses.
  - The Naval Officer's Guide, 1943; MS029.002.028.001 (Box Volume 28)
    Donated by Jason Samuels, graduated from NROTC at Tufts
    Navy; NROTC
  - Primer of Navigation, 1943; MS029.002.029.001 (Box Volume 29)
  - The Rules of the Nautical Road, 1941; MS029.002.030.001 (Box Volume 30)
    by Captain Raymond F. Farwell
  - The Bluejackets' Manual, 1943; MS029.002.031.001 (Box Volume 31)
- NROTC/V-12 Exhibit Materials, 1999 -- 2003; MS029.003; 1.75 Linear Feet
  This series contain exhibit materials used for the V-12/NROTC exhibits displayed in Tisch Library. Included are mounted labels and photographs from the V-12 collection and several reproduced photographic prints.
  - Exhibit I, 1999; MS029.003.031.001 (Box 31)
    Labels and mounted photographs and images.
  - Exhibit II, 2000; MS029.003.032.001 (Box 32)